So now I'm going
to show you how
to plant a listicle
not to be confused
with testicles. Sorry could
not resist. Oh man
nearly 40.
I haven't slept. I
haven't been to bed.
Can you tell? Now
if you didn't skip
phase two, which hopefully
you didn't, we have
already done a listicle
in our demo video
but I'm going to
show you how to
plan them again now.
So a listicle is
pretty much most YouTube
videos. They're basically just
points that don't connect
step by step. So
I made 300 videos
and learned this. Top
five exercises for beginners.
Five clues to spot
a narcissist. Most videos
even if they don't
have numbers in the
title are listicles. So
the pros of these
are they are kind
of easy to produce
and there's no real
structure to them but
actually I don't know
sometimes I feel that
makes it a bit
easy to watch. So
with process and deep
dive you're kind of
giving them steps to
action. With a listicle
it's the sort of
thing someone could watch
in the toilet and
be like I got
value from that. Like
they don't have to
go and actually action
anything. Although you should
give them actual things.
They're great for storytelling
and kind of sharing
your journey. They are
then easy to repurpose
into social content if
you are that sort
of person who does
that. Some viewer types
don't like them. Mine
don't like them at
all. I've had one
do well and what
I realized was that
my viewers just don't
want to hear about
10 random steps. They
just want to give
them a process over
and over again. On
film booth, completely different.
And that's the thing
about YouTube. It's annoying.
You have to figure
out what our viewers
want. All right cons.
Also easy to put
off viewers. So if
one part of your
list isn't that interesting
to them then you
can turn around and
go yeah I'm off.
So it's tricky keeping
them hooked and what
that means is you
need strong transitions at
the start of each
of your points so
that they care about
listening. So who should
make them? White belt
beginners, blue belt novices,
black belt pros, basically
everyone. Who likes watching
them? Learners who want
quick hits of insight.
They're very good for
like complete beginners because
they're not too overwhelming.
Casual viewers who are
kind of new to
the topic. Scroll stoppers.
People who are looking
for like fast takeaways
and they are best
used to share quick
lessons from your experience
to give chunks of
advice that don't link
together when each point
can stand alone without
a step -by -step
teaching. And the secret
sauce is like I
said make transitions very
strong hooks so they
care about the information
that follows. So if
you're a beginner, you're
going to want to
make sure that you're
not going to have
to do the same
thing over and over
again. You want to
keep the point fast
and clear. So give
one story then one
lesson. You want to
tie your lessons back
to your viewers top
problems over and over
again. Mistakes. Don't be
too vague or broad
with the information you
talk about. Viewers still
like kind of specific
information to their problems.
Don't give weak titles
or overuse phrases like
the brutal truth about
knitting. Because if you're
a beginner, you're going
to want to keep
that in mind. Because
if you're a beginner,
you're going to want
to keep that in
mind. It's not going
to match or exceed
their expectations. So be
careful. I see a
lot of people copy
Hormozy and his aggressive
titles and then they
don't match the expectations.
So the strategy for
this, just brain dump
your lessons, then refine
and then structure each
one in motion logic.
So often a listicle
video kind of looks
like this. Point one,
we have a visual
demo, contrast, a breakdown.
We show the problem,
we give a story,
it's a metaphor to
simplify it. Then we
give the logical step
to get the result.
Same over and over
again. Now titles. There's
loads. Could be anything
really. Here's some examples.
I'm not going to
read them out. You
get the idea. Don't
just go using these
thinking Ed's done all
the work for me.
I haven't. I just
made these up and
they're often, they're kind
of similar to ones
you see on YouTube
a lot. But keep
in mind, some of
your viewers won't like
listicles. Thumbnails. You can
use any strategy. You
just need to make
viewers ask how, what,
why. Production. Keep it
simple. And what I'd
recommend doing is to
use a listicle. You
can use a listicle.
You can use a
listicle. You can use
a listicle. I think
the best way to
do that is to
do a listicle. So
what I'm doing is
breaking up your list
using tech chapters. So
if you're doing five
mistakes after each mistake,
flash mistake number three
on screen, just so
viewers know where they
are. Then when we
get to the emotion
part, you can show
the problem contrast the
old way versus the
new way and a
visual demo. You can
break down, you can
tell a story or
metaphor. We've already spoken
about that. And then
when the logic break,
one thing to think
about is like, these
aren't necessarily for big
depth or big steps.
It's often about fast,
simple information. So. I
wouldn't go into a
20 step process for
fixing something in the
middle of a listicle.
It'd be too much.
End screen. If you
are optimizing for views
as your main goal,
push it to the
previous version of this
video template. If you
have made a previous
one, otherwise just push
it to the next
logical video that makes
sense for your viewers.
Optimizing for sales, push
it to high converting
sales video, optimizing for
emails, push it to
a high converting email.
Now we have done
in the demo video.
So although I've kind
of been over this
in the demo video,
I'm going to go
over it again here.
I'm We can see
the intro has the
hook, the problem result,
the self transition. So
let's read out. Did
you think growing a
channel would be easy?
I did. So that's
the relatable question hook.
I did. I made
over 300 YouTube videos
and eventually generated millions
of views. So my
gosh, it was such
a grind. I really
wish I could have
done things smarter to
speed up results. So
the problem, I made
all these videos and
it was tough. And
then we set up
the value of the
video to come to
make your business's journey
10 times easier. Here's
40 brutal truths and
about growing a business
as YouTube channel. I
wish I'd known a
lot sooner. Why on
earth did I not
reuse that intro recently?
It's a good intro.
Play by your own
rules, boy. And then
we transition into the
emotion brick and in
a listicle when you're
just listing lessons, the
transition can literally just
be lesson number one.
Now, also what I
would say is that's
a boring transition.
If you want to
hook them, and I
said that transitions are
important here, I would
probably just go around
and tie the lesson
into a result. Lesson
number one is going
to stop you from
worrying about people who
comment on your videos
ever again. Lesson number
one is going to
get you more consistent
sales and leads, something
like that, right? So
probably not the best
transition, if I think
about it. Naughty.
And then we go
into the emotion brick.
So all I'm doing
is telling a story
in this case. Have
you ever noticed how
none of your friends
and family really seem
to care about your
YouTube channel? When I
told my friends I
was starting one, they
just said, okay, and
moved on. That's heartbreaking,
isn't it? I'm not
sure if I'm going
to be able to
do that. I'm not
sure if I'm going
to be able to
do that. But here's
the truth. Most people
won't understand why you're
doing this or how
tough it actually is.
They think it's going
to be easy. You
just point the camera.
And then we move
on to the logic,
but we'll give a
lesson. That's why it's
so important you find
others who share your
YouTube session. So lesson
number one is to
connect with like -minded
creators. Start a group
chat, support each other,
because when they learn,
you'll learn. And this
one simple hack will
keep you motivated and
speed your progress. Oh,
I'm laboring the point
there. Should have cut
that out. And then
bosh, we transition into
the next emotion brick
with a boring transition.
So I'm going to
go into the emotion
brick. And then I'm
going to go into
the boring transition I
should have tied a
result to. And off
we go again. So
that's just one way
of doing it. Cool
thing about my scripts
is I read them
back and I go,
what is this crap?
Which is great because
it means I'm still
improving. Okay. So now
let me show you
how to plan a
list of cool. So
you click on here.
We've got some examples
of mine and other
people's. They might not
follow my exact structure.
Keep in mind, this
is my IP. You
might not see this
used on other channels.
So don't go looking
for it going, why
aren't they using Ed's
system? It's probably because
they're not paid me
to get it. You
have to stick to
the thing you paid
for. All right. So
first things first, always
set your goal, sales,
emails, or views. What
do you want, baby?
And then you put
your thumbnails and titles,
all three of them
ready for the split
tester. Then we work
out our top three
questions based on our
packaging. Then we do
a messy brain dump.
So you just want
to list all of
the ideas, all the
things you might want
to talk about in
this video. Don't worry
about order. Just get
it out of your
head. Use skyscraper bot
to research. Other people's
videos just to help
level up your plan
and make sure you
put things of viewers
love. And then you
refine that messy plan
into points, reduce the
clutter, bring things down
to only the things
that are going to
match and exceed viewers
expectations.
And then you plan
the emotion brick for
each point that is
there from one of
these. And then you
can use this emotion
brick decision matrix to
help you work out
which is the best
option to use at
that point in time.
So it might be
a little bit faster,
but it's not as
much of a hassle
if you're doing it
the right way. You
can do it in
a way that you
can actually make it
work. So I'm going
to do that. So
the emotion brick is
simply going to show
viewers the problem they
have and the result
of using a shortcut.
So that might be
a visual demo going,
okay, this next tip
is going to save
you 10 minutes per
video per photo edit.
So right now you're
probably spending about 15
to 20 minutes doing
this, cutting out an
image and it's a
right pain in the
ass. But look, you
can actually do it
in this and then
you cut and it's
like instantly done. And
then you turn around
and that's it. You're
done. That's the emotion
brick. So now let
me show you the
shortcut to save 15
minutes per photo. Now,
then we have our
conversion strategy and you
can see here what
I've done is I've
planned the conversion strategy
after point one, where
in that case, I
might turn around and
go, and by the
way, if you want
to save three hours
per edit, check out
the link below. I've
got my top 20
Photoshop shortcuts you're going
to love and then
move on. So if
you're optimizing for emails,
get in that lead
magnet. If you're optimizing
for sales, you want
to get in your
call to action or
just keep it stealth
like I do. We're
just constantly showing viewers
results. If you're optimizing
for views, don't link
to anything, just get
them to your end
screen and then move
on to writing it,
upload, and then follow
my measurement system that
I'm going to teach
you where all you
do is go, did
you hit your goal?
If you did, ask
why and repeat it.
If you missed it,
ask why, avoid it
and remove the emotion.
Remember, all we have
to do is get
data we then react
to. That is our
number one goal.